In the early 1960s, the BBC broadcast a
documentary series that was unparalleled
in its ambition and scope.
Over 26 episodes, the series told the
story of a conflict that affected
virtually every family in Britain and
most of the world. Those
who had lived through the Great War
[music] remembered it as vividly as
ever.
>> I never seen so many dead men
clumped together as what I saw then. And
I thought to myself, "Oh, the world's
dead. They're all dead. They're all
dead."
The first idea sort of flitted through
my mind was that the end of the world
had come and this was the day of
judgment.
More than 250 eyewitnesses were filmed
for the Great War series, but only a
tiny fraction of the recorded interviews
made it to air.
[music]
50 years after they were filmed, this
program presents the very best of the
original interview material.
Most of it is shown here for the very
first time, restored and [music]
digitized in high definition.
This is the closest we'll ever get to
what it was really [music] like for
those who were there.
One had no sanity in the business at
all.
When the war was not very [music]
active, it was really rather fun to be
in the front line.
>> And I thought to myself, well, if this
is death, it's not so bad.
>> What was it that we soldiers stabbed
each other, strangled each other, went
for each other like mad dogs? [music]
We was very happily married, very very
happy because we was very much in love
and he thought the world of me and I
thought the world of him.
And then it came to be that the war
started.
Well, we had a friend over in Canada
that had enlisted over there and he came
over here and he came one night and
asked us would we go to the uh palace.
He'd booked seats for the palace and
would we go. We didn't know what was on
of course and it was a great treat for
us. So we went. When we got there, the
palace, everything was lovely and best
Tilly was recruiting, which we never
knew till we got there. I wouldn't have
gone if I'd have known, of course.
Anyway, she uh was dressed on the stage
beautifully, beautiful gown, either
silver or gold. I'm not quite sure, but
it was an evening gown. And she also had
a big union jack lap around her. And she
introduced that song, we don't want to
lose you, but we think you ought to go.
We don't want [singing] to lose you, but
we think you [music] ought to go for
your king and your country.
[singing]
[music]
>> I was walking down the Camden Town High
Street when two young ladies approached
me and said to me, "Why aren't you in
the army with the boys?" So I said,
"Well, I'm sorry, but I'm only 17."
Oh, we've heard that one before. She put
her hand in a bag and pulled out a
feather. I raised my hand, thinking she
was going to strike me when this feather
was pushed up my nose.
>> We were sat at the front and she walked
down and she hesitated a bit and she put
her hand on my husband's shoulder.
And all the all the place was full of
the boys following her down and they
couldn't really get on the stage. Not
all of them couldn't. And he was with
one of them. He got up and he went with
her.
[singing]
>> A sergeant came out of one of the shops
and said to me, "Did she call you a
coward?" I said, "Yes." And I felt very
indignant at the time. He said, "Well,
come across the roadway to the drill
hall and we'll soon prove that you're
not a coward." And then the sergeant
said to me, "How old are you?" I said,
"I'm 17." He said, "What did you say?"
19. He took my height and he says,
"Now," he says, "we'll go around to the
doctor for a medical exam.
[music]
>> [music]
>> I got round to the doctor and I was told
to take all my clothes off which
embarrassed me very very much. Any rate,
I got back to the drill hall and there
were six of us and the sergeant called
out, "Mr. Lang." I walked forward and I
thought, "Oh, that's good." I'm not in.
And he says, "You're the only so and so
that's passed out of this six." And to
my amazement, I found that I was being
called Private S Lang.
I was terribly upset and I said, uh, I
didn't want him to go and be a soldier,
uh, because, uh, I didn't want to lose
him. I didn't want him to go at all.
But he said uh we have to go. He said
there has to be men to go and fight for
the women otherwise he said where should
we be?
[music]
I can remember shortly after arriving in
the front line in the morning, there was
what they used to call the pom pom, a
German gun they used to bring up to
their trenches with a view to popping
them into our trenches. It used to go
pom from their side and arrive at ours
with a pom. Well, they used to infilate
us along [music] starting in the left
hand side and coming along and uh on
this particular morning one reached
right at the side of me and a fellow who
was on sentry go there or just watching
the no man's land to see there was no
movement by the Germans and this shell
from the pom pom arrived and blew half
his head off. Well, that was my
initiation into death.
And you'd hear in the distance quite a
mild pop as the gun fired 5 miles away
and then then um a humming sound as it
approached you through the air growing
louder and louder until it was like the
roar of an airplane coming into land on
the tarmac.
There comes the moment when the shell is
right on top of you and your nerve would
break and you'd throw yourself down in
the mud and cringe in the mud till it
was passed. Some of the shells were
passing over you probably 3T 4 foot and
the air was an inferno.
You and your mind of course was another
inferno. You were completely reason was
completely blast out of it.
Our dark outs crumbled. They fell upon
us and we had to dig ourselves and our
comrades out. Sometimes he found them
suffocated,
sometimes smashed to pulp.
Soldiers in the bunkers became
hysterical. They wanted to run out and
fights develop to keep them in the
comparative safety of our deep bangers.
Even the rats became hysterical.
They came into our flimsy shelters to
seek refuge from this terrific artillery
fire.
[music]
You were in a maze and you felt that at
any time if you relaxed control, you
went haywire. And it was quite common
sight to see people that had relaxed
control get up and run around in circles
like a sheep. And of course they ran
round for some time until they met
Shellfire, which finally finished them.
There were ways in which you could
maintain your self-control.
And there is some strange connection
between small physical actions.
If you um um hum a little tune to
yourself and feel that you can quietly
get through this tune before the next
explosion, it gives you a sort of
curious feeling of safety.
or you start drumming with your fingers
on your knee and and have an an
quite irrational desire to complete this
little ritual. The the these minute
things uh uh uh protect you from the
nervous collapse which may come at any
moment.
[music]
One had no sanity in the business at all
because you got in this position where
the inferno was so blasting that you had
no time to think and you could feel as
you laid down on the ground. You could
literally feel your heart pounding
against the ground. And that was the
sort of condition you found yourself and
in a continuous bombardment which lasted
sometimes for hours. The emotional
strain was absolutely terrific until
when you got the order to advance, it
seemed that it was a sort of a a release
from that bondage.
We stood there packed like sardines,
unable to even stand up in comfort.
Men were fast asleep on the feet. Others
just stood scared into the cloudless
sky. The lady next to me had checked his
rifle and his ammunition over and over
again, but apparently still not
satisfied.
Others just stood instead,
silent at the grave, maybe looking
forward.
And we still had another hour to wait.
I remember those lads standing there
dead silent, couldn't make a noise.
The fellow next to you, you he was your
best friend. You looked at him. You
probably didn't know him the day before.
And then an hour ago, they were the
longest those hours. than the shortest
hours in life.
>> I never dreamt that even borrowed time
could go so slowly.
I'd advanced before many times. I wasn't
afraid of advance. I didn't like it, but
I wasn't afraid of it.
But I was afraid.
I was afraid of myself. I wondered
if I would live long enough to get out
of the trench. And if I did,
would I have enough puff left in me to
cover that 400 yd or so in one mad rush?
And if not, would I have enough courage
left to rise again and face that rain of
lead?
Left hand commander Parson, my company
commander, he had the most confident
smile. Turned around and says, "Five
minutes to go, men.
Four minutes. 3 minutes. 2 minutes.
One minute to go, man. Are you ready?
Come on, boys. Off we go.
[music]
Then 5 minutes to go and then zer and
all hell lets loose.
There's our barrage, the Germans
barrage, and over the top we go.
I asked God to help me as I scrambled
over the top into that withering fire.
Many, many men were killed as soon as
they showed their heads and fell back
into the trench. Poor old left-handed
Commander Parsons only got a few yards.
[music]
As soon as you get over the top,
fear has left you in its terror.
You don't
look, you see.
You don't hear, you listen.
Your nose is filled with fumes and
death. You taste the top of your mouth.
It weapon and you are one.
Haunted you back to the jungle. The
beneer of civilizations dropped away.
I felt that someone kicked me in the
chest and down I went.
Later on, I found myself crawling about
on the bottom of the trench trying to
find my rifle. My face was stiff and I
can only see out of one eye.
I eventually got to my rifle and I
realized that all my equipment had been
torn to shreds. Apparently, a machine
gun sweeper caught me and blew the lot
up and down I went.
We all stopped and laid down
trying to get what shelter we could from
the tremendous rifle fire which was
coming over.
And then a sergeant just in front of me
jumped up and said, "Come on men, be
British." We jumped up and followed him.
He he ran about six yards and he went
down.
Well, we ran on about another 20 yards
toward the German trenches. The German
trenches were literally literally
packed. They were standing about four
deep firing machine guns, rifles at
straight at us. And uh they were
gradually picking us off.
And uh there was only myself and one
other chap that weren't hit.
As we withdrew over the ground that had
been captured that day, the sight was
incredible. It was just like a a flock
of sheep lying asleep in [music] a
field. And it became evident that the
regimental stretcherbears who one time
had been bandsmen [music] had been
unable to cope with such a huge number
of casualties.
Quite a number of the men were still
alive and they were crying out and
begging for [music] water. They plucked
our legs as we went by. One hefty
[music] chap did grab me around both
legs and held me. And I was going to
take the cork out of my water bottle to
[music] give him a drink. And I was
immediately prodded on by behind by
someone saying, "Get on. Get on. We're
going to lose [music] touch with a
column in front. We shall get lost."
Uh, in the years that have passed, that
man's pleadings have haunted me.
[music]
>> [music]
>> We at no sooner withdrawn ourselves from
this shambles and got together what we
could than we began to build up the
regiment again and get ready for the
next time. And this seems to me
extremely difficult to explain.
Now um I had lost both my officers and
all my sergeants and three twothirds of
my men and um here I was I was 20 years
old
young acting captain and I had to begin
to form a new company. Well, to begin
with, I was in a state of complete
physical and mental frustration.
And I think for a few days after the
battle, I was getting near having a
nervous breakdown. But when one is
young, um, uh, physical rest very
quickly puts that right. In quite a few
days, I was almost as good as ever. This
seems to me very strange. Um, we got a
draft of a hundred very good men up from
the base. Then we started all over again
and had a new company. And at the end of
a month, we were ready to do it again.
And this seems to me the strangest thing
of all when I look back on it.
During the time that he was away, I was
very very lonely as I didn't make
friends very easily and uh all the
thoughts I had was for my husband and uh
it was times was very very hard and I
only had 12 and six a week and therefore
I couldn't go out and spend like anyone
else
and I used to sit at night and tried to
do a bit of reading or a bit of sewing
with my hands to pass the time away like
that. But it was very very hard and uh
me times would wonder and wonder what he
was doing or if he was thinking about me
and uh wondering how he was going on
when I should when I should see him
again and all things like that. Keep the
home fires [music]
burning [chanting]
while your hearts are
[music] yours are far away.
My father and my brother were at the
front and later my youngest brother and
my mother worried very much and her only
means of knowing whether they were alive
was reading the casualty lists
and we children used to gather around
and and listen and watch and look over
her shoulder even while she read them
and the tension was felt by us all. Were
they alive? Were they still with us?
>> When I got home to my parents, my father
was a soldier himself.
He didn't ask any questions. But mother
used to ask all kinds of questions. Why
is has there got to be a war? And what
are you doing there? And can you have
your bath regularly? And all those
questions were which a mother would ask
and I couldn't give any answers or the
answers I gave were very short and not
very satisfactory for mother when my
father and my brothers uncles relatives
different sorts and friends when they
came home on leave as they frequently
did and they were either staying in our
house or visiting our house
I noticed a strange lack of ability
to communicate with us, to tell us what
it was really like.
They they would perhaps make a joke that
you feel sounded hollow. There was
nothing to laugh about.
[singing]
[music]
>> This world of the trenches was entirely
a man's world.
women had no part in it. And when one
went on leave, what one did was to
escape out of the man's world into the
woman's world. And one found that um
however pleased one was to see one's
girlfriend. And I'm speaking only of the
light emotions of a boy, not of the the
deeper feelings of a happily married
man. um one could never somehow quite
get through. However nice and
sympathetic they were, um the girl
didn't quite say the right thing. And
one was curiously upset, annoyed by
attempts of well-meaning people to
sympathize, which only reflected the
fact that they didn't really understand
at all. Oh, we'll [singing] never tell
[music] them. No, we'll never tell them.
There was [singing] a front. But if we
[music]
knew,
>> there was a loud knocking on the door.
Such a big knocking on the door. And
this voice shouted, "Open the door. The
Jerry's are here." See? So, uh, my
mother said, "Oh," she said, "It's
Percy. I can tell his voice. And in he
came, you know, all mucky and what have
you, right from France.
He only got six days leave and in two
days traveling out of that had to be
taken off the six days. So he didn't
have very long. And he said, "No." He
says, "Now kitty, call me kitty." He
says, "Now kitty." He says, "What
[music] would you like for a present?
I'm going to buy you a present while I'm
home." I said, "Oh, [music] I don't
know." I said, "You, but I was I'm
afraid I was rather vain at those days
and I was rather attractive girl." And
[music] I said, "You know, I've seen a
beautiful hat down the street." "Oh, it
is a lovely hat." I said, "I would like
it." And it was in a shop window and I'd
looked at this hat several times and it
was a lovely hat and I'd have loved it,
but it was such a terrible deer hat. And
he said, "Well, come on." He said,
"Well, go down and have a look at it."
And I'll never forget that hat. It
[music] was white felt and it turned up
all around and with me being dark and it
[music] had a a mau big mauve feather
all the way in the brim and it hung
over. Oh, it was gorgeous.
We got dressed up after I got this hat.
He bought it me and I took him to the
works, Noble Leather Works, where I
worked and I introduced him to Mr. noble
it himself and they all shook hands with
him and how pleased and proud I was when
he went in the leather works and
everybody could see him
girl I remember she said why don't you
stay on a little longer they can very
well do without you there and I said
don't you know that there is something
like duty
Oh, duty. That's not It's you. There are
so many people who never went to war.
Why have you got to go to war?
>> They were restless at home. They didn't
want to stay home. They wanted to get
back to the front.
They always would express a desire to
finish it.
>> In the end, I only had the wish to go
back.
It It was as if I were were going home
to my soldiers.
He went back about the Thursday night, I
should think, no longer than that. I
didn't go with him to the uh to the tram
because there was trams those days, you
know, there was no buses, there was
trams. I didn't go with him to the tram.
One of my brothers went with him
and a friend of his. And he told his
friend, it seems afterwards, he told me,
he said, "I'm afraid I shall never come
back again."
Anyway, he went and uh and then I I
found out that I was pregnant.
[music]
Pack up your troubles in your old kit
[music] bag and smile smile smile
[music]
while you elucifer to light your bag.
Smile boys. [music and singing]
When the war was not very active, it was
really rather fun to be in the front
line. It was not very exacting and
indeed it was not very dangerous. One
was having a sort of outofdoor camping
holiday with the boys with a slight
spice of danger to to to make it
interesting.
[music]
We were billeted in Arantier most of the
summer, a very pleasant summer. It was a
quiet sector of the line.
And u evening if we were not on duty in
the trenches, we used to go out into the
town and go to the nearest stamina,
which is the equivalent of the English
local, and behind the bar would be
Madame. And we hoped one or two of her
daughters, very attractive. And um when
we'd had our suppers and the omeletes
were cleared away and the coffees
coffees were disposed of and other
drinks put round, we used to sing. The
um the popular popular song of course at
the time was Madmoiselle from Aranadel.
You didn't have to know the reason.
>> The girls used to ask us to translate
them afterwards, but we couldn't very
well do that. They were not uh not
suitable for translation. The verses
weren't.
>> Towards evening, we suddenly heard
singing in the trenches.
Not a shot was fired anywhere. Neither
from from the Russians nor on the on the
part of the Austrians. And suddenly that
singing.
[music]
And soon after that our soldiers started
singing too.
And to my greatest surprise, those boys
who sang used to sing all kinds of songs
except hymns started to sing Easter
hymns.
about 11:00
I saw a Christmas tree going up on the
German trenches and there was a light
and we stood still and we watched this
and we talked and then a German voice
began to sing a song
and
after that somebody come over Tommy come
over some of us went over at once And
very soon we were exchanging gifts. The
whole of no man's lands, far as we could
see, was gray and khaki. There they
were, smoking and talking, shaking
hands,
exchanging names and addresses after the
war to write to one another.
One of my advanced posts reported that
the Russians had thrown something into
their hole into that dugout.
And and I said, "Well, what what is it?
What was it?" And they said, "We don't
know. We don't know whether we can touch
it." Well, of course, you've got to
touch it. You've got if it's hand
coronates, you've got to throw it out.
But have a look and report again. And
one minute later they reported it was
Easter eggs. Real Easter eggs cordily
painted which the Russians had rolled
slowly into their hole.
A few minutes later they the Russ a few
Russians came along and said got any
vodka for us or any
any cigarettes?
Well, the boys had a few cigarettes, but
they had no vodka.
That kind of armistice lasted all Easter
Sunday.
[music]
The Germans started burying their dead,
which frozen out. And we we picked up
ours and buried them. And little crosses
of ration boxwood
were nailed together, quite small ones,
and indelible pencil they would put the
Germans
for Viland unfight
for fatherland and freedom. And I said
to a German, "Excuse me, but
how can you be fighting for freedom?
you started the war and we are fighting
for freedom. And he said, "Excuse me,
English comrade,
but we are fighting for freedom for our
country."
And I say you also put here rest in God,
an unbeanter held here rest in God, an
unknown hero in God. Oh yes, God is on
our side. Blessed he's on our side.
Well, English comrade, do not let us
quarrel on Christmas Day.
As the war progressed and stunt
followed stunt, uh it required that we
should live in animal conditions and in
doing so
it was inevitable that we developed the
animal characteristic of killing. And
apart from the short feeling of
nervousness as you knew that you were
moving up to carry out another
operation, there was a feeling of
exaltation that once again you were
going to be able to extract retribution
from the fellows that had killed your
mates.
I was confronted
by a French corporal.
He with his bayonet at the ready and I
with my bayonet at the ready.
For a moment
I felt the fear of death and in a
fraction of a second
I realized that he was after my life
exactly as I was after his.
I was quicker than he was.
I tossed his rifle away and I ran my
bayionet through his chest.
He fell, put his hand on the place where
I had hit him and then I thrust again.
Blood came out of of his mouth and he
died.
I suddenly felt physically ill. I nearly
vomited. My knees were shaking. And I
was quite frankly ashamed of myself.
My comrades were absolutely undisturbed
by what had happened.
One of them boasted that he had killed a
French soldier with a butt of his rifle.
Another one had strangled a captain. A
third one had hit somebody over the head
with his spade.
What was it that these soldiers
stabbed each other, strangled each
other, went for each other like mad
dogs? What was it that we who had
nothing against them personally
fought to them fought with them to the
very end and death?
We were civilized people after all.
One
evening I was warned that I had to go on
a firing party, six of us, to shoot four
men of another battalion who had been
accused of desertion.
Well, I was very worried about it
because
uh I didn't think it was right in the
first place that uh Englishmen should be
shooting other Englishmen. I thought we
were in France to fight the Germans.
I thought that I knew why these men had
deserted if they had deserted because
I understood their feelings which and
what would make them desert.
The fact that they'd probably been in
trenches for two or three months without
a break
absolutely
broke the nerve
when you hadn't had sleep for several
nights and when you hadn't had rest and
sometimes hardly a meal. It did get you
and you reached a point where there was
no beyond. You just could not go any
further. And that's the point I'd
reached.
I was tired of all the carnage, of all
the sacrifice that we had there, just
again about 25 yards. And then I began
to think of those poor devils who had
been punished for self-inflicted wounds.
Some had even been shot. and I began to
wonder how I could get out of it.
>> An old soldier in our battalion [music]
told me that uh it was one thing in the
army which you could refuse. So I
straightway went back to the sergeant
and said, "I'm sorry. I'm not doing
this."
And I heard no more about it.
I think one reason why I felt so strong
about it was the fact that a week before
a boy in our own battalion had been shot
for desertion. Well, I knew that boy and
I knew that he absolutely lost his
nerve. he couldn't have gone back into
the line. And uh he was shot. And the
tragedy of that was that a few weeks
later in our local paper,
I saw that his father had joined up to
avenge his son's death on the Germans.
[music]
In the distance, I heard the rattle of
harness.
I didn't hear much of the wheels, but I
knew there were ammunition wagons coming
up. And I thought to myself, well,
here's a way out. When they get level
with me, I'll oo e ease out and put my
leg under the wheel. I should bound to
get away, and I can plead it was an
accident. Well, I waited and the sound
of the harness got nearer and nearer.
Eventually, I saw the leading horse's
heads in front of me and I thought,
"This is it."
And I began to ease my way out. And
eventually, the first wagon reached me.
And you know, I never even had the guts
to do that. I found myself wishing to do
it, but hadn't got the guts to do it.
>> [music]
>> After the Germans had stopped shelling a
little while, we heard one of their big
ones coming over. My pal shouted and
threw himself down.
I was too damn tired even to fall down.
I stood there. Next, I had a terrific
pain in the back and the chest, and I
found myself face downwards in the mud.
My pal came to me. He tried to lift me
up. And I said to him, "Don't touch me.
Leave me. I've had enough. Just leave
me."
The next thing I found myself sinking
down in the mud. And this time, I didn't
worry about the mud. I didn't hate it
anymore. But it seemed like a protective
blanket covering me. And I thought to
myself, well, if this is death, it's not
so bad.
I heard the postman come and I knew that
it would be a letter for me. So I ran
down in me night dress and opened the
door and snatched the letter off the
postman and uh run in shut the door in
my night dress and me bare feet and I
opened the letter and it was from his
sergeant and it was it just said dear
Mrs. Mortar I'm very sorry to tell you
of the death of your husband. Well that
was as far as I could read. You see I
couldn't read anything else. So I uh I
didn't know just for a few minutes what
happened but I ran out I ran out of the
house as I was me bare feet and I I
banged on the next door the next door
neighbor and uh it was a Mr. and Mrs.
Hurst and they let me in and whatever's
to do she said and I said will you read
this letter Mrs. Let's read this letter.
And she said, "Oh." She says, "You a
poor child.
I found myself being bumped about and I
realized that I [music] was on a
stretcher." And I thought, "Poor devils,
these stretcher bears. I wouldn't be a
stretcher bearer for anything." And then
something else happened. I suddenly
realized that I wasn't dead. I realized
that I was alive.
I realized that if these wounds didn't
prove fatal, that I should get back to
my parents, to my sister, to the girl
that I was going to marry.
The girl that had sent me a letter every
day practically from the beginning of
the war.
And I must then have [music] had that
sleep that I so badly needed. for I
didn't recollect anymore until I found
myself in a bed with [music] white
sheets and I heard the lovely, wonderful
voices of our nurses, English, Scotch,
and Irish. And I think then I completely
broke down.
>> I thought, well, perhaps it's just an
error.
I wasn't sure what had happened. I
thought it's perhaps just an error. But
later on I uh I wrote to the sergeant. I
wrote and answered his letter and I
found out later on I had another letter
to say that the man that had sent me
word had also been killed.
>> Next the party was sitting beside the
bedside.
He was trying to comfort me. He told me
I'd had an operation and he told me that
he had some relatives out there that had
been out there right from the beginning
and by God's grace they hadn't had a
scratch. He said, "They've been lucky,
haven't they?" I thought to myself,
"Lucky. Poor devils.
After I found that it was officially
known that he had been killed, I used to
pass me time away trying to make little
baby clothes for my baby. And eventually
the baby became to be born. It was born
at home, but uh I don't remember it
being born at all. I had a very bad
time. I had two doctors and I don't
remember the baby being born and I felt
I didn't want to live. I had no wish to
live at all because the world had come
to an end then for me cuz I'd lost all
that I'd loved.
>> [music]
>> when an old lady came along and she
called across and said, case are
finished.
Well, it really didn't mean a thing to
us because the war had gone on so
[music] long and it seemed that one
couldn't accept the fact that the war
would ever finish.
I was sitting at a table with a major in
the Scots grays and he had a large
old-fashioned
hunting [music] watch which he put on
the table and he watched the mits going
round. [music]
11:00 came and I remember he shut his
watch up and said, "I wonder what we're
all going to do next." And that was very
much the feeling of everyone. What was
one going to do next? Uh to some of us
it was the end of of four years to some
of 3 years or some less. Uh to some of
us it was practically the only life we'd
known.
No more very lights going up with their
greenish wavering flare.
No liies of the dead in the night.
No flash of heights on the horizon.
No drowned droning of the shells.
No machine guns. No patrols going out.
Just nothing.
Silence.
[music]
I'm
in the air.
>> [music]